<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proposalls from his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax: and the Councell of his Army, by way of addresse to the Parliament, for removing the causes of the cryes and groanes of the people; for pay for the souldiers, relief for Ireland, disbanding the supernumery of forces in England. And removing of the quarters further from London, into severall parts. Also for inabling the kingdome to finde monies, and for making commodities to be cheaper, and more plentifull the High Sheriffes and not committees to execute the power. To prevent the designes of those that study anarchy; to remove distractions, and grindings of the faces of the poore, and the wasting of the counties, and to settle a true peace, and security through the whole kingdome. By the appointment of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of his Army, subscribed John Rushworth, Secretary. October 17. 1647. ... Imprimatur, G. Mtt.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E411_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202102</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862508</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862508</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84929)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 65:E411[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proposalls from his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax: and the Councell of his Army, by way of addresse to the Parliament, for removing the causes of the cryes and groanes of the people; for pay for the souldiers, relief for Ireland, disbanding the supernumery of forces in England. And removing of the quarters further from London, into severall parts. Also for inabling the kingdome to finde monies, and for making commodities to be cheaper, and more plentifull the High Sheriffes and not committees to execute the power. To prevent the designes of those that study anarchy; to remove distractions, and grindings of the faces of the poore, and the wasting of the counties, and to settle a true peace, and security through the whole kingdome. By the appointment of his Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of his Army, subscribed John Rushworth, Secretary. October 17. 1647. ... Imprimatur, G. Mtt.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Ibbitson, in Smithfield, neer the Queenes-head Tavern,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Appropriations and expenditures --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Finance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PROPOSALLS From his Excellency Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX: AND The Councell of his Army, by way of Addreſſe to the Parliament, for removing the cauſes of the Cryes and Groanes of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; For pay for the Souldiers, Relief for <hi>Ireland,</hi> Disbanding the ſupernumery of Forces in <hi>England.</hi> And removing of the Quarters further from <hi>London,</hi> into ſeverall parts.</p>
            <p>Alſo for inabling the Kingdome to finde Monies, and for making Commodities to be cheaper, and more plentifull <hi>The High Sheriffes and not Committees to execute the power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent the Deſignes of thoſe that ſtudy Anarchy; to remove diſtractions, and grindings of the faces of the poore, and the waſting of the Counties, And to ſettle a true peace, and ſecurity through the whole KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>By the appointment of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Councell of his Army, <hi>Subſcribed JOHN BUSHWORTH,</hi>Secretary.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>October 17. 1647.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THeſe Propoſals from his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi>and his Councell, are appointed to be Printed, according to the Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>G. M<hi rend="sup">tt.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Robert Ibbitſon,</hi> in Smithfield, neer the Queenes-head Tavern, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proposals">
            <pb facs="tcp:161221:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161221:2"/>
            <head>PROPOSALS From His Excellency Sir <hi>THOMAS FAIRFAX</hi> AND The Councell of his Army, by way <hi>of Addreſſe to the Parliament, for removing</hi> The Cauſes of the cryes and groanes of the PEOPLE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe great ſenſe we have of the cryes and groanes of the people, under Free quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and thoſe unutterable calamities, that muſt inevitably befall this poore King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, preſſes us ſore, And invites us to make this earneſt addreſſe unto you; that you would pleaſe to take it into your preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration to make out a proviſion for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant pay of thoſe forces you intend to keepe on foote for the ſecurity of this Kingdome,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161221:3"/>and the reducement of diſtreſſed <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe His Excellency and this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my are oblieged by their ingagement to take care of all thoſe Forces, which have mutual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ingaged with you, in theſe late ſervices.</p>
            <p>We doe offer unto you our opinion; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may not much conduce to your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, ſpeedily to prepare moneys for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of ſuch as you intend not to be of the number of that ſtanding body of Horſe and Foote, for the ends aforeſaid: That ſo your Forces being contracted, the Kingdome may be better incouraged and more enabled to make good their pay, and the Army be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the reſpective Garriſons, and ſuch Quarters that the price of commodities may not be inhauced in any part of the Kingdom, (much leſſe ſo neere this populous City) which is occaſioned by this contracted po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
            <p>Truly Sir we might preſſe you with that moneths pay which hath beene ſo often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and we did beleeve was before this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited in your Treaſury, And that great neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect (which muſt reſt ſome where) that no part of it is drawen in: And that if the City
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161221:3"/>be the fayler, the ſad preſident it gives to the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>We might mention unto you the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Souldiery: And the great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages ſome that ſtudy Anarchy, and deſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons take upon it, to make their impreſſions upon this Army.</p>
            <p>But nothing is ſo difficult and grievous to us, as to conſider how the poore Souldier (for his meere ſubſiſtance) is compelled to grind the faces of the poore, to take a livelihood from them, who are fitter to receive almes, to undo families, waſt counties, threaten the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the whole, and al propriety, &amp; to be an abhorring to himſelfe (which ſome ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of them acknowledge) and this for want of that conſtant ſupply and pay, whereby they might chearefully and with content to the people diſcharge their quarters, and ſo eaſe both the Country and their own mindes of an intollerable burden,</p>
            <p>This being that which the neighbour States both of the Netherlands and others make their prime ſcope, and whereby they injoy ſo much peace, and quiet, under a warlike po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, this being the only and certain <hi>medium</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:161221:4"/>to ſtop the cries, and groanes of ſo many thouſands ready to periſh, and to heale the wounds of this deſolate Nation, that will otherwiſe bleed to death, and inevitable ruine.</p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>Wee doe humbly conceive, that the preſent and ſpeedy diſpatch of what wee here offer, is the only Baſis, and foundation for the reſt of your Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, how weighty ſoever they ſeeme to be. And without which you cannot anſwer to this Kingdomes, peace, or ſafety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee ſhall onely adde, that for the bringing in your aſſeſſements, it may bee moſt contenting, and effectuall too; To paſſe it by the way of the High-Sheriffe, &amp;c. As it uſed to be in the Caſe of Subſidies, the Name and power of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes being ſo unpleaſant to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the High Sheriffe being ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſall,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161221:4"/>both for his Eſtate, and power in the County.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee would not have put thus much trouble upon you, but that it is to eaſe you and the Kingdome of a greater, and to diſcharge our ſelves before God and men, as thoſe that have moved every ſtone by our ſeverall addreſſes to accompliſh that without which the Kingdomes peace and ſecurity cannot be eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee doe further offer unto you, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity of a preſent Auditing, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares of this Army, and that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for the Army, may be forthwith diſpatched, with full inſtructions to that purpoſe, according to your late Vote, which being put into a way, would give great ſatisfaction to the Souldiers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And wee ſhall againe re-minde you of our humble deſire, that the Arreares, and Publique Faith of the Army, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161221:5"/>Souldiery of the Kingdome may be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed out of the Deanes and Chapters Lands, &amp;c. or ſuch other viſible way as ſhall be contenting to the Souldiery; And what ſhall bee reſolved upon in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe to be inſiſted upon with the reſt of the Propoſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Putney <date>the 7. of October, 1647.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>By the Appointment of his Excellency Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of his Army, Signed, <hi>JOHN R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SHWORTH</hi> Secretary.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
